[{"question":"Similarity between plant and animal flagella microtubules is:","a":"9+3","b":"9+2","c":"9+6","d":"9+1","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Living beings are made up of cells. This statement belongs to:","a":"Lamarck","b":"Von Helmont","c":"Hugo de vires","d":"Schleiden and Schwann","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Identify the statement that does not hold true for  a cukaryotic cell?","a":"Presence of 80S type of ribosome in the mitochondria.","b":"Presence of 80S type of ribOsome in the cytoplasms","c":"Pre fmitochondria containing circular  DNA.","d":"Presence of membrane bound organelles.","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Mitochondria supply most of the necessary biological energy by:","a":"Breaking down of sugur","b":"Oxidising substrates of TCA cycle","c":"Reducing NADP","d":"Breaking down of protein","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Prokaryotic cell does not have:","a":"Nucleolus","b":"Membrane bound organelles","c":"Centrioles","d":"All of the above","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Which one of the following cell organelles is found only in plants?","a":"Golgi complex","b":"Mitochondria","c":"Plastids","d":"Ribosomes","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"In which of the following organisms, plastids  are not found?","a":"Blue green algae","b":"Bacteria","c":"Fungi","d":"All of these","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Function of centriole is:","a":"Formation of spindle fibres","b":"Formation of nucleolus","c":"Initiation of cell division","d":"Formation of cell plate","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Cristae are found in:","a":"Surface of grana","b":"Surface of plasma membrane","c":"Wall of mitochondria","d":"Nuclear membrane  (a) Photooxidation 19. Match column-I (scientists)","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Three morphological forms of golgi complex are :","a":"Lamellae, tubules and vesicles","b":"Cisternae, tubules and vesicles","c":"Cisternac, tubules and lamcllac","d":"Granum, thylakoids and vesicles","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Which of the following organelles are double membrane-bound? ","a":"Nucleus","b":"Chloroplast","c":"Mitochondria","d":"All of the above","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Which of the following substances is most Likely To permeate a membrane by diffusing Directly through the lipid bilayer? ","a":"K'","b":"Glucose","c":"CH","d":"0Â²","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Plasmodesmata connections help in:","a":"Cytoplasmic streaming.","b":"Synchronous mitotic divisions.","c":"Locomotion of unicellular organisms.","d":"Movement of substances between cells.","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Both chloroplasts and mitochondria:","a":"have multiple membranes.","b":"have highly structured innemost membranes.","c":"are found only in eukaryotic cells.","d":"All of the above","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Which of the face ofgolgi complex is Associated With ER? ","a":"Forming face i.e., Trans-face","b":"Maturing face i.e, Trans-face","c":"Both forming and maturing face","d":"Forming face or Cis-face","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Schleiden and Schwann proposed:","a":"phenomenon of Brownian movement","b":"cell theory or cell doctrine","c":"protoplasm as a physical basis of life","d":"None of the above","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Centrioles and centrosomes are present in cells of:","a":"Bacteria","b":"Cyanobacteria","c":"Green plants","d":"Animals","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"The principal protein of cilia and flagella is:","a":"Tubulin","b":"Nexin","c":"Myosin","d":"Albumin","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"lon carriers are located in:","a":"Nucleus","b":"Cell wall","c":"Cellular space","d":"Plasma membrane","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Which of the following organelles is directly connccted to the outer membranc of the nucleus in a ukaryotic cell? ","a":"Mitochondrion","b":"Lysosome","c":"Golgi apparatus","d":"Endoplasmic reticulum","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"The four basic shapes of bacteria are:","a":"amoeboid, elongated, biconcave and coccus.","b":"clongated, bacillus, coccus and amocboid.","c":"bacillus, coccus, vibrio and spirillum.","d":"bacillus, amocboid, clongated and coccus.","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"The polynucleated condition appeared by free nuclear division without cytokinesis is:","a":"Syncytium","b":"Coenocytic","c":"Found in amphibian oocyte","d":"All of these","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Which of the following limits the movement of molecules when carrier-mediated facilitated diffusion is involved?","a":"Concentration gradient","b":"Availability of carrier molecules","c":"Temperature","d":"All of the above","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Which one of the following combination is  mismatched?","a":"Glycocalyx May be capsule or slime layer","b":"Pili -Reproduction","c":"Cell wall - Protective, determines shape, prevents from bursting","d":"Flagella, pili and fimbriae Surface structures of bacterial cellFlagella, pili and fimbriae Surface structures of bacterial cell","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Which one of the following combination is  mismatched?","a":"Glycocalyx May be capsule or slime layer","b":"Pili -Reproduction","c":"Cell wall - Protective, determines shape, prevents from bursting","d":"Flagella, pili and fimbriae Surface structures of bacterial cellFlagella, pili and fimbriae Surface structures of bacterial cell","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Which of the following is related to Glycosylation Of protein? ","a":"Endoplasmic reticulum","b":"Peroxisome","c":"Lysosome","d":"Mitochondria","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Which of the following is present in both prokaryotes and eukarvotes?","a":"Lysosome","b":"Vesicles","c":"Chloroplast","d":"Plasma membrane","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Which structure is present in chromosomes? (b) Centromere","a":"Nucleus","b":"Centromere","c":"Centrosome","d":"Golgi body","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Select the incorrect statement about prokaryotic ribosomes.","a":"50S and 30S subunits unite to form 70S ribosomes.","b":"Polysome/polyribosome consists of many ribosomes only.","c":"Ribosome is the site of protein synthesis.","d":"Polysome indicate the synthesis of identical polypeptide in multiple copies.","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Which of the substance is a complicated mixture of glycerol + phellonic acids deposited on  d on cork  cells to make it impermeable to water?","a":"Silica","b":"Cutin","c":"Lignin","d":"Suberin","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"In nucleoplasm, a conspicuous body of spherical shape attached to a particular chromosome on a definite position is called","a":"plasmid","b":"karyolymph","c":"nucleolus","d":"nuclear reticulum","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"F particles /oxysome/ elementary particles are present in:","a":"Endoplasmic reticulum","b":"Chloroplast","c":"Mitochondria","d":"Golgi complex","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Which of the following lacks cell wall?","a":"Gametes","b":"Amoeba","c":"Mycoplasma","d":"All of these","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Protein synthesis in an animal cell occurs:","a":"on ribosomes present in cytoplasm as well as in mitochondria. ","b":"on ribosomes present in the nucleolus as well as in cytoplasm. ","c":"only on ribosomes attached to the Nuclear Envelope and endoplasmic reticulum. ","d":"only on the ribosomes present in cytosol.","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Which of the following types of junctions Are Responsible for communication between cells? ","a":"Tight junctions","b":"Desmosomes","c":"Gap junctions","d":"None of the above","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"When mitochondria are actively engaged in phosphory and clectron transport, it is: ","a":"in active state","b":"in condensed state","c":"having enlarged intermembrane space","d":"All of these","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Gas vacuoles are not reported in","a":"Cyanobacteria","b":"Purple/green photosynthetic bacteria","c":"Amoeba","d":"Prokaryotes","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Which organclle is surrounded by a Double Phospholipid bilayer with many large pores? ","a":"Nuclear envelope","b":"Plasma membrane","c":"Golgi apparatus","d":"Mitochondrion","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Which organclle is surrounded by a Double Phospholipid bilayer with many large pores? ","a":"Nuclear envelope","b":"Plasma membrane","c":"Golgi apparatus","d":"Mitochondrion","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Similarity between plant and animal flagella microtubules is: ","a":"9+3","b":"9+2","c":"9+6","d":"9+1","hint":"","correct":"b"}]